Chapter 11. V as in victory. P, B, F, and V are all popped. When pronounced
correctly, V shouldn't stand out too much. Its sound, although noticeable, is small.
As a result, people depending on their native language sometimes confuse V with
B, Spanish, Japanese, with F, German, or with W, Chinese, Hindi. These four sounds
are not at all interchangeable. The W is a semivowel and there is no friction or
contact. The B, like P, uses both lips and has a slight pop. Americans tend to have a
strong popping P. You can check your pronunciation by holding a match, a sheet
of paper, or just your hand in front of your mouth. If the flame goes out, the
paper wavers, or you feel a distinct puff of air on your hand, you've said P, not B.
B is the voice pair of P. Although F and V are in exactly the same position, F is a
hiss and V is a buzz. The V is the voice pair of F. When you say F, it's as if
you're whispering. So for V, say F and simply add some voice to it, V, which is
the whole difference between fairy and very, as you'll hear in our next exercise.
The F, too, presents problems to Japanese who say hh. To pronounce ff, the lower lip
raises up and the inside of the lip very lightly touches the outside of the upper
teeth, and you make a slight hissing sound. Don't bite the outside of your lip
at all.